Guide to the Samuel Smith Wood Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Smith Wood papers
1849-1920
MS 1083
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
The papers consist of correspondence relating to the life of the Samuel Smith Wood family in Greytown, Nicaragua, the bombardment of the city by the American ship, Cyane, in July, 1854, and claims rising out of that incident. A particularly long account is given in a letter (July 15, 1854) by Wood's son, Alexander McCready Wood. Also in the papers are letters (1849) by Samuel S. Wood to his wife describing a trip through the gold regions of San Juan and San Francisco, California and a family genealogy.
Wood, Samuel S., 1799-1881
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection also available on microfilm (788 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM164.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1959-1962.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 164 instead of the originals.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel Wood Papers date 1849-1920 and are principally concerned with the Wood family of Greytown, Nicaragua, and the bombardment of Greytown by the American ship Cyane in 1854.
The rush across Central America by Forty-Niners bound for California resulted in a backwash of Americans who remained there to engage in trade. Those gathered at San Juan del Norte, or Greytown, organized themselves into an independent free-trade city. Among the prominent merchants of this place was Samuel Smith Wood who carried on an extensive and lucrative business. Among the more substantial citizens, Wood possessed a large and valuable stock of merchandise and was the owner of a number of buildings at Greytown.
In 1854, a dispute broke out between some of the residents of Greytown and the American minister there, and the United States government dispatched the ship Cyane to investigate. An account of what followed is given in a lengthly letter written by Alexander McCready Wood, son of Samuel Smith Wood, dated 1854 July 15. He writes: "The Cyane arrived here on Tuesday night last and on Wednesday morning Captain Hollis notified the inhabitants of our town that indemnification to the amount of $28,000 was demanded by his government and unless the terms were complied with by eight o'clock on Thursday morning, he would blow and bombard the town to atoms which the inhabitants failing to do, his threat was actually and faithfully carried into effect and our once pleasant little town lies in a heap of smouldering ruins."
Captain Hollis' act, which was generally condemned, gave rise to numerous actions against the American government. The Wood family presented a memorial to Congress asking indemnity for their large losses. Many of the papers are concerned with this case.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Smith Wood worked in flour manufacturing in New York City until ca. 1826. He moved to a farm in Coutlandville, where he remained until 1834. Wood then went to California prospecting for gold. In 1852 he established a trading post at San Juan del Norte (Greytown), Nicaragua.
Gold mines and mining -- California; California -- Gold discoveries; Latin America; Nicaragua -- Foreign relations -- United States; San Juan del Norte (Nicaragua); United States -- Foreign relations; Merchants; Wood, Alexander McCready, 1829-1881; Wood, Samuel S., 1799-1881
- Inventory
  - "Wood Family Pedigree", 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Correspondence
    - 1849 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - 1850-1851 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - 1852 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - 1853 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - 1854 Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - 1854 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - 1855 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - 1855 May-Aug (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - 1855 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - 1856 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - 1857 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
    - 1857 Apr-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - 1858 Jan (Box 1, Folder 14, Reel 1U)
    - 1858 Feb-Dec (Box 1, Folder 15, Reel 1U)
    - 1859 Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - 1859 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 17, Reel 1U)
    - 1860 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 18, Reel 1U)
    - 1860 May-Dec (Box 1, Folder 19, Reel 1U)
    - 1861 (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
    - 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
    - 1865-1871, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 22, Reel 1U)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23 - 25, Reel 1U)